<?xml version="1.0"?>
<status>

  <developers>
	  <person name="Ethan Cerami"      email="cerami@cbio.mskcc.org"      id="cerami" />
  </developers>

  <changes>
    <!-- Add new releases here -->
    <release version="0.2" date="beta release">
      <!-- Some action types have associated images. By default, images are
      defined for 'add', 'fix', 'remove', 'update' and 'hack'. If you add
      src/documentation/resources/images/<foo>.jpg images, these will
      automatically be used for entries of type <foo>. -->

      <action dev="cerami" type="add">
	      Added cPath Administrator Functionality:  Administrator can now run the 
	      full text indexer, and upload files for import.  Administrator can also
	      monitor long-term tasks, such as importing of large PSI-MI XML documents.
	      Admin page is now also password-protected.
      </action>
      <action dev="cerami" type="add">
	      Created cPath Diagnostics page to perform routine tests and verify
	      correct installation.
      </action>
      <action dev="cerami" type="add">
	      Added support for loading of external references.  Users can use the admin.pl
	      command line utility or the Admin page to import references.
      </action>
      <action dev="cerami" type="add">
	      Added generic framework for pre-computing specific cPath queries.  Queries
	      can be run from the admin.pl script or set to run on a *nix cron job.
      </action>
      <action dev="cerami" type="add">
	      Performed load-testing via Apache JMeter.  JMeter config scripts are now
	      available in config/cpath_load_testing_plan.jmx.
      </action>
      <action dev="cerami" type="add">
	      Added new page for displaying Interactor specific information, including:
	      name, organism, and all external references.
      </action>
      <action dev="cerami" type="update">
	      Updated the Installation notes to include information re:  cPath 
	      diagnostics page, Tiny Monitor, and "where to look when things to wrong."
      </action>

      <!-- Sample action:
      <action dev="JB" type="fix" due-to="Joe Contributor"
          due-to-email="joec@apache.org" fixes-bug="123">
          Fixed a bug in the Foo class.
        </action>
        -->
    </release>
  </changes>

  <todo>
     <actions priority="medium">
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Add getExternalReferences to query API.  This would allow e.g. Cytoscape
	to easily create external links.
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Add support to cPath and data services layer for importing PSI-MI files that contain interactions
    	with more than two proteins (e.g. 5 protein complex).  This would allow us to import data
    	from the PIN database in the Tempst lab at MSKCC (http://pin.mskcc.org).    
	</action>
    </actions>
    <actions priority="low">
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Field Specific Lucene Searching, e.g. "name:RAS".
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Index all interactions (right now, we only index interactors).
	Requires changes to web interface.
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Build a Front-end administrative interface to the External Database Tables
        (more details are included in phase 6 doc, before being deferred)
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Add new query:  query by experimental method (e.g. all the data from two-hybrid).
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Provide query API functionality to get a list of valid query API commands.
        E.g. for getInteractionsBySource, we could have getValidSources.	
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	For HTML front end of cPath query API: paginate results (only text index 
	results currently paginated).
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Resolve cross-species interaction issue.
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Support content-length calculation of PSI-MI queries, where possible, to support more 
	accurate progress metering on the client side.  We might be able to easily do it 
	for queries that are cached and for the precomputed queries.  For queries that 
	aren't, we could at least provide updates of the parsing progress as it happens 
	(Rob's idea).
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
	Implement a full statistics page.  This could be precomputed regularly (e.g. weekly),
	not computed on the fly.  The best example of a stats page is currently the MINT page:
        http://160.80.34.4/mint/statistics/statistics.php.
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
		Prevent against cross-scripting vulnerability (validate user input before use).
	</action>
	<action context="cpath" dev="TBD">
		Set up auto-emails upon fatal cPath errors (how does a user deal with errors?).
	</action>
	<action context="dataservices" dev="TBD">
		Add an Ontology object to the dataservices bio package to allow retrieval of Gene 
		Ontology type information.	
	</action>
	<action context="dataservices" dev="TBD">
		Add Gene Name/Synonym Look up to data services (requires a back-end, may be able to 
		use Entrez Gene DB).
	</action>
	<action context="dataservices" dev="TBD">
		Create a service for reading in Cytoscape node/edge attributes to go with sif reader.
	</action>
	<action context="dataservices" dev="TBD">
		Create an "About Data Services PlugIn", with version #, list of all registered
	        (more details are included in phase 6 doc, before being deferred)
	</action>
	<action context="dataservices" dev="TBD">
		Resurrect the GRID Plugin - retrieves data from GRID directly into Cytoscape.	
	</action>

    </actions>
  </todo>
</status>
