<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Phase Development</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Phased Development">
      <p>
          cPath currently uses an iterative development cycle for developing
          new features.  At the beginning of each phase, we document
          a list of new features, and flesh out the functional
          requirements for each new feature.  We also provide technical
          details on how to intend to implement each new feature.
      </p>
      <p>
          The documents below contain information for each
          phase of cPath development so far.
      </p>
      <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Phase</th>
            <th>Summary</th>
            <th>Approximate Date of Completion</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase1.html">Phase 1</A></td>
                <td>Implemented the first version of the the Data Services
                Module.  The Data Services Module is a standalone library used
                by both cPath and Cytoscape to retrieve biological
                data from a diverse set of data sources.</td>
                <td>April, 2003</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase2.html">Phase 2</A></td>
                <td>Implemented the first version of the cBio web service API.
                The web service API was originally created to access a mirror
                of the GRID database, and has since been integrated into
                the core cPath code.
                </td>
                <td>June, 2003</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase3.html">Phase 3</A></td>
                <td>Continued expanding the Data Services Module, and
                    created Cytoscape specific PlugIns for accessing remote
                    data sets.
                </td>
                <td>July, 2003</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase4.html">Phase 4</A></td>
                <td>Continuted the Data Services Module, added support
                    for network state information, and built the first
                    prototype of the cPath web site.
                </td>
                <td>September, 2003</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase5.html">Phase 5</A></td>
                <td>Implemented the main cPath database tables for
                    importing and linking external data sets.
                </td>
                <td>November, 2003</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase6.html">Phase 6</A></td>
                <td>Implemented the core set of cPath tables, XML import/
                    export functionality, and full-text search functionality.                              </td>
                <td>December, 2003</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase7.html">Phase 7</A></td>
                <td>Implemented the Cytoscape Activity Center Plugin,
                and expanded the cPath Web Services API.  Released cPath
                beta 1 to the cBio web site.</td>
                <td>February, 2004</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase8.html">Phase 8</A></td>
                <td>Added cPath Admin functionality, created
                generic framework for pre-computed queries, completed
                load testing, created the developer site, and modified
                the look and feel of cPath with new stylesheets.
                Release beta 2 to the cBio web site</td>
                <td>March, 2004</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase9.html">Phase 9</A></td>
                <td>Finalize cPath for internal cBio/MSKCC Release.</td>
                <td>June, 2004</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase10.html">Phase 10</A></td>
                <td>Create Beta 2 Release of Cytoscape cPath PlugIn,
                import HPRD into cPath, create PSI-MI/SOFT PlugIns for
                Cytoscape 2.0, and misc. bug fixes.</td>
                <td>Septmeber, 2004</td>
          </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase11.html">Phase 11</A></td>
                <td>Focus on Neuroblastoma Use Case</td>
                <td>December, 2004</td>
          </tr>
            <tr>
                <td><A HREF="phase12.html">Phase 12-</A></td>
                <td>Starting in Phase 12, we have started to write up all phase
                documents on the cBio Intranet Wiki, available locally
                within MSKCC.  This is much easier, and much faster for us.
                If you would like copies of these phases,
                please send us an email, and we will be happy to provide
                them to you.</td>
                <td>Ongoing</td>
          </tr>
      </table>
     </section>
  </body>
</document>