<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <body>
        <section name="Phase 9:  About this Document">
            <P>This document describes functionality that will be built in
                Phase 9 of the Cytoscape / CPath project. The overall goal
                of Phase 9 is to prepare a complete beta release for
                internal use within cBio and MSKCC.  This includes:
                web UI tweaks, better integration of the cPath and the
                Activity Center Cytoscape PlugIns, and importing of a
                complete sample data set.
            </P>
        </section>
        <section name="1.  Refactor cPath Indexing/Searching to use
            Lucene Exclusively">
            <P>
            In the current cPath architecture, we support two types of searches:
            those that go through MySQL, and those that go through Lucene.
            For example, we filter by organism type by performing a SQL query
            on the CPATH.organism field;  however, we filter by keyword by
            performing a Lucene query.  In this phase, we plan to centralize
            all indexing/searching in Lucene.  This will provide a number of
            advantages, including a simplified architecture, support for field
            specific queries, and support for more advanced queries, including
            boolean operators, fuzzy searching, etc.
            </P>
            <P>
            As part of the refactoring, we will also do some performance
                measurements.  For example, we plan to index organism type in
                both mySQL and Lucene, and compare the performance of each indexing
                schema.
            </P>

            <subsection name="1.1  Add Search by Experiment Type">
                <P>Under Advanced Search, add search by experiment type.
                Make this available via Advanced Search HTML and Web Services
                API.
                </P>
                <HR/>
                <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  Do we have a list of experiment
                types?  Are we using the PSI-MI controlled vocabulary
                for experiment types?</P>
                <P>
                <UL>
                    <LI>Resolution:  We stick to the PSI-MI controlled
                    vocabulary.  The latest cv terms are available
                    at:  <A HREF="http://psidev.sourceforge.net/mi/controlledVocab/">
                    http://psidev.sourceforge.net/mi/controlledVocab/</A>.
                    For the web site front end, we can create a pull-down
                    menu of the 10-15 most common experimental types.</LI>
                </UL>
                </P>
                <HR/>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="2.  Finalize the cPath Web Site">
            <subsection name="2.1  General Tweaks">
            <P>
            We plan to go through each cPath page and tweak the User
                Interface (UI).
            </P>
            <P>
                <HR/>
                <B>Todo:  </B>
                Ethan, Gary and Rob to meet to review all cPath pages.
                <HR/>
            </P>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="2.2  Add Privacy Policy">
            <P>
            From Gary:  "Add privacy terms, etc. to web site - I'll prepare this."
            </P>
            </subsection>

        </section>

        <section name="3.  Update the Activity Center PlugIn">
            <subsection name="3.1  Update to Cytoscape 2.0">
            <P>The Activity Center PlugIn currently works with Cytoscape 1.1.
            We need to update it to work with Cytoscape 2.0.  Note that
            we need to maintain the Cytoscape 1.1 compatible code too, as
            Cytoscape 2.0 is still a few months away from being finalized.
            </P>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="3.2  Add Support for Preloaded Data">
            <P>Right now, the Activity Center requires that a user create
                a project file, indicating a network file, and a gene expression
                file.  We need to make this more generic so that we can support
                the following use case:
                <UL>
                    <LI>User loads graph from file menu.</LI>
                    <LI>User load expression matrix file from file menu.
                    </LI>
                    <LI>User runs Activity Center algorithm on the already
                    loaded data.</LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="3.3  Modify Activity Center PlugIn to recognize
                Affymetrix IDs">
            <P>
            In order to function correctly, the Activity Center requires two
                sets of data:  a network graph and a list of expression values.
                These two data sets must use common identifiers.  However, when
                retrieving data from cPath, interaction data will be
                specified in PSI-MI XML Format, and the primary identifier
                (usually specified in the names/shortLabel element) is not likely
                to match the identifier used in the expression data file.  Hence,
                the PlugIn will not work correctly.
            </P>
            <P>
            This should be a relatively simple fix.  For simplification, we assume
            that the expression data is specified with Affymetrix IDs, and we also
            assume that cPath is preloaded with Affymetrix IDs, and that those
            Affymetrix IDs are specified in proteinInteractor/xref/primaryRef or
            secondaryRef.  We then update the PlugIn to match graph data with
            expression data via the Affymetrix ID.
            </P>

            <HR/>
            <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  Is it OK if we currently assume Affymetrix IDs
            in the expression data file?  Or should we allow the user to pick
            from a list of ID options?</P>
            <P>
                <UL>
                <LI>Resolution:  It's ok to assume Affy IDs for first pass -
                    asking the user to specify the ID type is a definite must
                    for a general implementation, but is not imperative.
                    Affy IDs are likely the only ones we'll see for
                    MSKCC gene expression data.
                </LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
            <HR/>
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="4.  Update the cPath PlugIn">
            <P>
                The cPath PlugIn is part of the overall Data Services
                PlugIn, and only works in Cytoscape 1.1.  We therefore need to:
                <UL>
                    <LI>Separate out the cPath PlugIn, and make it standalone.</LI>
                    <LI>Update the cPath PlugIn so that it is Cytoscape 2.0
                    compatible.</LI>
                </UL>
            </P>

            <HR/>
            <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  Should we include the SOFT Reader in the
            cPath PlugIn?  Or Keep it out for now?</P>
            <P>
            <UL>
                <LI>Resoution:  Let's keep the SOFT and PSI-MI plugin
                    separate from the cPath plugin for now.</LI>
            </UL>
            </P>
        </section>

        <section name="5.  Make cPath / Activity Center PlugIns available
            from cPath Web Site">
            <P>
                <UL>
                    <LI>From the cPath site, provide links to both the
                        cPath PlugIn and the Activity Center PlugIn.</LI>
                    <LI>Provide PDF Manual with Tutorial overview and instructions.
                    </LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
            <P>
                For our current purposes, we are considering the following
                three use cases:
                <UL>
                    <LI>Use Case 1:  User wants to import a specific set of
                    data into Cytoscape.  This requires use of the generic
                    data services plugin.</LI>
                    <LI>Use Case 2:  User wants to query cPath from within
                    Cytoscape.  This requires use of the cPath specific
                    query plugin.</LI>
                    <LI>User Case 3:  User wants to load network data from cPath,
                    superpose gene expression data and then run the Activity
                    Center Algorithm.  This requires multiple plugins, including
                    the cPath specific plugin, and the Activity Center Plugin.
                    These Plugins will be completely independent of one another,
                    and will not communicate directly.  Rather, the cPath plugin will
                    load data into the Cytoscape graph, and the Activity Center
                    Plugin will subsequenly operate on that graph.</LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
        </section>

        <section name="6.  Load External Data Sets">
            <P>
            We plan to import a complete sample data set.  This will  include:
                <UL>
                    <LI>IntAct</LI>
                    <LI>DIP</LI>
                    <LI>MINT</LI>
                    <LI>HPRD</LI>
                    <LI>BIND:  If we can fit in a BIND to PSI-MI XSLT, we
                    might want to do it, otherwise we should wait for BIND
                    to convert their data to PSI-MI (probably this summer).
                    </LI>
                    <LI>Affymetrix Identifiers</LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
            </section>

        <section name="7.  License Issues">
            <P>
            From Gary:  "The LICENSE.txt file that is currently in the cpath
            root directory in CVS contains the text that we should be putting
            at the top of all the source code files.  We should also have the
            full LGPL license checked in as LICENSE.txt and the copyright
            should be called COPYRIGHT.txt.  Do we have any other licenses
            that we are required to distribute right now?  If so, we
            should just make a license subdirectory and put all the current
            license related files in there too instead of in the root."
            </P>
        </section>

        <section name="8.  Finish Developer Site">
            <P>
            From Gary:  "Finish dev site e.g. install ViewCVS (This will require
            a move of our CVS repository, which I've talked to Joanne about -
            we'll have to pick a time to do this and coordinate)."
            </P>
        </section>

        <section name="9.  QA Period">
            <P>
            Allocate 3-5 days of comprehensive testing of cPath / PlugIn
                testing.
            </P>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
