<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <body>
        <section name="Phase 10:  About this Document">
            <P>This document describes functionality that will be built in
                Phase 10 of the Cytoscape / cPath project. The overall goals
                of Phase 10 are to:  complete the Beta 2 version of the Cytoscape
                cPath PlugIn,  import HPRD into cPath, fix misc. cPath bugs
                currently logged in Mantis, and repackage the PSI-MI / SOFT
                PlugIns for Cytoscape 2.0.  In addition, Phase 10 will include
                javadocing of the current jar/class loader classes in Cytoscape,
                and background reading for the cPath scientific use case(s).
            </P>
        </section>
        <section name="1.  Complete Beta 2 Version of cPath PlugIn">
            <P>
            We released the Beta 1 version of the cPath PlugIn a few months ago.
            However, this version of the PlugIn has two serious limitations:
                <UL>
                <LI>you can only load a maximum of 100 interactions at a time.</LI>
                <LI>you cannot interactively select nodes / edges and view
            details about them.
                </LI>
            </UL>
            Both of these issues must be resolved in order for us to proceed
            with our scientific use cases.
            </P>

            <subsection name="1.1  Enable Importing of Larger Data Sets">
                <P>This is really a two part problem.  The first part
                    requires changes to the cPath Web Services API and
                    is already complete.  The new API enables client applications
                    to select specific pages of results -- for example, if a 
                    client applications wants 500 interactions, it can make 10
                    different requests and receive 50 interactions back for each
                    request.  Full details are available in the revised
                    web services help page (now checked into cvs).
                </P>
                <P>The second part of the problem is to update the cPath PlugIn
                    to make use of the new Web Services API.
                </P>
                <P>Specific details include:
                <UL>
                    <LI>Add support for new web services API (obviously).</LI>
                    <LI>Add Progress bar for monitoring "Get All Interactions"
                    w/ estimated time left.  We can get fairly accurate time
                    estimates, and display these to the users (very important).</LI>
                    <LI>Add a stop button, so that a user can cancel long
                    requests (very important).</LI>
                    <LI>Add a confirmation panel.  For example, if a user
                    requests all human interactions, we pop open a panel that
                    says:  "XXXX interactions match your query.  This will
                    take approximate YYY minutes.  Do you want to proceed?"
                    (very important).</LI>
                    <LI>Add error handling for the event that cPath / network
                    is interrupted.  For example, what happens if we have 500
                    of 1000 interactions, and the network link is broken?</LI>
                    <LI>Add error handling for low memory.  We should add
                    some memory monitor so that we can inform users of low-
                    memory problems before a generic Out of Memory error occurs.
                    </LI>
                    <LI>Add Warnings to the application mappers.  Warnings
                    are not as severe as exceptions, and can be displayed to
                    the end user.</LI>
                </UL>
                </P>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="1.2  Enable Selection of Nodes / Edges">
                <P>
                In the Beta 1 version of the PlugIn, we provided a interactive tree UI
                where users could select an interaction or an interactor
                in the left panel, and immediately view details in the right
                panel.  With potentially thousands of interactions,
                the tree UI is no longer practical, and the Beta 2 version will
                no longer contain it.  However, we will maintain the interaction
                / interactor detail panels.  When a user selects a node or edge
                in the main Cytoscape window, these panels will immediately 
                display details.  This mainly requires that we update the
                PlugIn UI, and listen for specific node / edge selection events.
                </P>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="2.  Import HPRD into cPath">
            <P>
            This is a long-standing item.  Some of the difficulty comes from
            erroneous data from HPRD, and some of the difficultly comes from
            existing cPath code that does not properly validate PSI-MI data
            (e.g. garbage in, garbage out).  A few bugs in Mantis address
            the issue (See <A HREF="http://www.cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000458">Bug #458</A>,
            <A HREF="http://www.cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000497">Bug #497</A>.)
            </P>
        </section>
        <section name="3.  Misc Bug Fixes">
            <P>We have 15 existing bugs in Mantis.  Ethan and Gary need to prioritize
            these and fix them.</P>
        </section>
        <section name="4.  Create PSI-MI Import / Export PlugIn for Cytoscape 2.0">
            <P>Create a separate PSI-MI Import / Export PlugIn for Cytoscape 2.0,
            and post to the cytoscape.org web site.  This should be very easy.</P>
        </section>
        <section name="5.  Create SOFT Import PlugIn for Cytoscape 2.0">
            <P>Create a separate SOFT Import PlugIn for Cytoscape 2.0, and post to
            the cytoscape.org web site.</P>
        </section>
        <section name="6.  Cytoscape Specific Items">
            <P>Most of Phase 10 will be devoted to cPath and the cPath PlugIn.
            However, there are a few useful items of Cytoscape work that are
            included in this phase:
            <UL>
                <LI>Misc. changes to the cytoscape.org web site.</LI>
                <LI>As first step towards refactoring the
                Cytoscape jar/class loader, I will take a crack at commenting
                /javadocing the existing code.  Before I make any changes,
                I want to understand the current code more completely --
                and will solicit documentation/history/comments for Andew,
                Rowan, Paul, and anyone else who might have knowledge of
                the existing code.</LI>
                <LI>Evaluate <A HREF="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/discovery/">
                Jakarta Commons Discovery Library</A>, for possible inclusion
                in Cytoscape core.
                </LI>
            </UL>
            </P>
        </section>
        <section name="7.  Background Reading">
            <P>
            As part of background reading for our scientific use cases,
            I'll be starting with four articles intially sent to me by Gary:
            </P>
            <P>
            <UL>
                <LI>Lockhart DJ, Winzeler EA, Genomics, gene expression and DNA arrays.
                [<A HREF="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=10866209">Pub Med Reference</A>]</LI>
                <LI>Vijver MJ, et. al.,
                A gene-expression signature as a predictor of survival in breast cancer.
                [<A HREF="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12490681">Pub Med Reference</A>]</LI>
                <LI>Huang ES, Black EP, Dressman H, West M, Nevins JR.,
                Gene expression phenotypes of oncogenic signaling pathways.
                [<A HREF="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12963829">Pub Med Reference</A>]</LI>
                <LI>Evans WE, Relling MV.,
                Moving towards individualized medicine with pharmacogenomics.
                [<A HREF="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=pubmed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15164072">Pub Med Reference]</A></LI>
            </UL>
            </P>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
