<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <body>
        <section name="Phase 9:  About this Document">
            <P> This document describes functionality that will be built in
                Phase 9 of the Cytoscape / CPath project. The overall goal
                of Phase 9 is to prepare a complete beta release for
                internal use within cBio and MSKCC.  This includes:
                web UI tweaks, better integration of the cPath and the
                Activity Center Cytoscape PlugIns, and importing of a
                complete sample data set.
            </P>
        </section>
        <section name="1.  Finalize the cPath Web Site">
            <subsection name="1.1  General Tweaks">
            <P>
            We plan to go through each cPath page and tweak the User
                Interface (UI).
            </P>
            <P>
                <HR/>
                <B>Todo:  </B>
                Ethan, Gary and Rob to meet to review all cPath pages.
                <HR/>
            </P>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="1.2  Add Privacy Policy">
            <P>
            From Gary:  "Add privacy terms, etc. to web site - I'll prepare this."
            </P>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="1.3  New Feature in Advanced Search">
                <P>Under Advanced Search, add search by experiment type.
                Make this available via Advanced Search HTML and Web Services
                API.
                </P>
                <HR/>
                <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  Do we have a list of experiment
                types?  Are we using the PSI-MI controlled vocabulary
                for experiment types?</P>
                <P>
                <UL>
                    <LI>Resolution:  We stick to the PSI-MI controlled
                    vocabulary.  The latest cv terms are available
                    at:  <A HREF="http://psidev.sourceforge.net/mi/controlledVocab/">
                    http://psidev.sourceforge.net/mi/controlledVocab/</A>.</LI>
                </UL>
                </P>

                <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  We currently only store interaction
                type in the XML fragment.  Searching would therefore be very
                slow.  Do we want to add a new field in the CPATH table
                for experiment type?  Or, should we store it in the
                EXTERNAL_DB table, and indicate that we are pointing to an
                external PSI-MI controlled vocabulary list?  This needs some
                more thought.
                </P>
                <HR/>
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="2.  Update the Activity Center PlugIn">
            <subsection name="2.1  Update to Cytoscape 2.0">
            <P>The Activity Center PlugIn currently works with Cytoscape 1.1.
            We need to update it to work with Cytoscape 2.0.
            </P>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="2.2  Modify Activity Center PlugIn to recognize Affymetrix IDs">
            <P>
            In order to function correctly, the Activity Center requires two
                sets of data:  a network graph and a list of expression values.
                These two data sets must use common identifiers.  However, when
                retrieving data from cPath, interaction data will be
                specified in PSI-MI XML Format, and the primary identifier
                (usually specified in the names/shortLabel element) is not likely
                to match the identifier used in the expression data file.  Hence,
                the PlugIn will not work correctly.
            </P>
            <P>
            This should be a relatively simple fix.  For simplification, we assume
            that the expression data is specified with Affymetrix IDs, and we also
            assume that cPath is preloaded with Affymetrix IDs, and that those
            Affymetrix IDs are specified in proteinInteractor/xref/primaryRef or
            secondaryRef.  We then update the PlugIn to match graph data with
            expression data via the Affymetrix ID.
            </P>

            <HR/>
            <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  Is it OK if we currently assume Affymetrix IDs
            in the expression data file?  Or should we allow the user to pick
            from a list of ID options?</P>
            <P>
                <UL>
                <LI>Resolution:  It's ok to assume Affy IDs for first pass -
                    asking the user to specify the ID type is a definite must
                    for a general implementation, but is not imperative.
                    Affy IDs are likely the only ones we'll see for
                    MSKCC gene expression data.
                </LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
            <HR/>
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="3.  Update the cPath PlugIn">
            <P>
                The cPath PlugIn is part of the overall Data Services
                PlugIn, and only works in Cytoscape 1.1.  We therefore need to:
                <UL>
                    <LI>Separate out the cPath PlugIn, and make it standalone.</LI>
                    <LI>Update the cPath PlugIn so that it is Cytoscape 2.0
                    compatible.</LI>
                </UL>
            </P>

            <HR/>
            <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  Should we include the SOFT Reader in the
            cPath PlugIn?  Or Keep it out for now?</P>
            <P>
            <UL>
                <LI>Resoution:  Let's keep the SOFT and PSI-MI plugin
                    separate from the cPath plugin for now.</LI>
            </UL>
            </P>

            <P><B>Open Issue:</B>  What is the specific use case of someone using
            this PlugIn?  Will they 1)  query cPath;  2)  read in expression data?
            and then 3)  run Activity Center Algorithm?  Will this require that the
            two PlugIns can actually talk to one another, or just that they be loaded
            up together?  Should we bundle the two plugins together? Where will
            the user get the expression data?   Need to think about this some more.</P>
            <HR/>
        </section>

        <section name="4.  Make cPath / Activity Center PlugIns available
            from cPath Web Site">
            <P>
                <UL>
                    <LI>From the cPath site, provide links to both the
                        cPath PlugIn and the Activity Center PlugIn.</LI>
                    <LI>Provide PDF Manual with Tutorial overview and instructions.
                    </LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
        </section>

        <section name="5.  Load External Data Sets">
            <P>
            We plan to import a complete sample data set.  This will  include:
                <UL>
                    <LI>IntAct</LI>
                    <LI>DIP</LI>
                    <LI>MINT</LI>
                    <LI>HPRD</LI>
                    <LI>BIND:  If we can fit in a BIND to PSI-MI XSLT, we
                    might want to do it, otherwise we should wait for BIND
                    to convert their data to PSI-MI (probably this summer).
                    </LI>
                    <LI>Affymetrix Identifiers</LI>
                </UL>
            </P>
            <HR/>
            <P><B>Todo:</B>  Determine complete data set.</P>
            <HR/>
            </section>

        <section name="6.  License Issues">
            <P>
            From Gary:  "The LICENSE.txt file that is currently in the cpath
            root directory in CVS contains the text that we should be putting
            at the top of all the source code files.  We should also have the
            full LGPL license checked in as LICENSE.txt and the copyright
            should be called COPYRIGHT.txt.  Do we have any other licenses
            that we are required to distribute right now?  If so, we
            should just make a license subdirectory and put all the current
            license related files in there too instead of in the root."
            </P>
        </section>

        <section name="7.  Finish Developer Site">
            <P>
            From Gary:  "Finish dev site e.g. install ViewCVS (This will require
            a move of our CVS repository, which I've talked to Joanne about -
            we'll have to pick a time to do this and coordinate)."
            </P>
        </section>

        <section name="8.  QA Period">
            <P>
            Allocate 3-5 days of comprehensive testing of cPath / PlugIn
                testing.
            </P>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
