<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <body>

  <section name="Phase 3:  About this Document">
    <p>
	    This document describes functionality that will be built in Phase 3 of the 
	    Cytoscape Data Services project.  The focus of Phase 3 is to: 
	<UL>
		<LI>formalize a data services plug-in architecture, so that new developers can start 
			creating their own data services.</LI>
		<LI>finalize all documentation and javadocs for the data services layer.</LI>
		<LI>refactor the overall cytoscape build process.</LI>
		<LI>add the proposed licence info. to all source files.</LI>
		<LI>Add data services to the cytoscape core.</LI>
		<LI>Create a template ant build file for data service plugins and
			documentation on how to use it.</LI>
		<LI>Create a cytoscape mapper to map PSI properties to cytoscape
			nodes and edges, and create a sample visual style to go with it.</LI>
		<LI>create a PSI-Reader plug-in and distribute it via a JAR file.</LI>
	</UL>
    </p>
  </section>
  <section name="Feature #1:  Creating Data Service PlugIns">
   <P>
	   Supposing a new developer wants to create a new data service for XXXX, here are 
	   the proposed steps:
	  	<OL>
			<LI>Pick the type of service you want to create.  Currently, you can 
			pick from either "interactor" or "interaction".</LI>
			<LI>Create your service class.  This class must implement either the
			InteractorService or the InteractionService interface.</LI>
			<LI>Create a manifest file for your plug-in.  This is an XML file that
			is based loosely on the Eclipse plugin.xml file.  The file describes: 
			<UL>
				<LI>Unique Service ID</LI>
				<LI>Service Description</LI>
				<LI>Version Number</LI>
				<LI>Provider Name</LI>
				<LI>Class name which implements the service</LI>
				<LI>Default Location (usually a URL)</LI>
			</UL>
			Below is a sample manifest file:
<source>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;data_service&gt;
    &lt;id&gt;ncbi_interactor_service&lt;/id&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;Retrieves sequence data from NCBI.&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;1.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;provider&gt;Memorial Sloan Kettering&lt;/provider&gt;
    &lt;class_name&gt;org.mskcc.dataservices.live.interactor.ReadInteractorsFromNcbi&lt;/class_name&gt;
    &lt;default_location&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov:80/entrez/query.fcgi&lt;/default_location&gt;
&lt;/data_service&gt;
</source>
		</LI>
			<LI>Move your manifest file to the root "dataservices" directory.</LI>
		</OL>
	</P>
	<P>Upon startup, the data services framework locates all manifest files, and registers 
		them with the central data services factory.  To retrieve a data service, 
		you must know its unique service ID.  If you don't know the corrrect service 
		ID, use the DataServiceFactory listServiceDescriptions() method to retrieve all 
		services and extract the ID, as needed.
	</P>
	<P>Below is sample code for accessing sequence data from the NCBI Data Service:
<source>
DataServiceFactory factory = DataServiceFactory.getInstance();
InteractorService service = (InteractorService)
factory.getService("ncbi_interactor_service");
Interactor interactor = service.getInteractor("6320569");
</source>

   </P>
   </section>
   <section name="Feature #2:  Refactoring the Build Process">
	   <P>This has been described in detail on the cytostaff mailing list.  For details,
		   refer to the mailing list.
	   </P>
   </section>
   <section name="Feature #3:  Application Mappers">
	   <P>So far, our technical architecture has described data service mappers.
		   These mappers take in data in one specific format, and map this data to
		   our intermediate biological objects (e.g. interactors and/or interations).
		   However, a second type of mapper also exists.  For lack of a better word,
		   these will henceforth be referred to as <I>application mappers</I>.  An application
		   mapper takes in intermediate biological objects and maps these to 
		   application specific data structures.  For example, the Cytoscape application
		   mapper will take in interactor and interaction objects, and map these to
		   Cytoscape nodes and edges.
	   </P>
	   <P>
		   To make these concepts clear, the diagram below shows an updated version of the 
		   data services architecture.  Data service mappers are denoted in blue on the
		   right side of the diagram.  Application mappers are denoted in organge on the 
		   left side of the diagram.
	   </P>
	   <P>
		   <image src="images/ds_overview.jpg"/>
	   </P>
	   <P>
		   As part of Phase 3 we will create a base cytoscape mapper that maps
		   basic interation and interactor data.  We will also create a PSI specific mapper
		   that extends the base mapper to map PSI specific data.  In the future, others
		   can extend the base mapper to provide additional levels of detail as needed.
	   </P>
   </section>
</body>
</document>
