<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <body>
  <section name="Phase 5:  About this Document">
    <P>
	    This document describes functionality that will be built in Phase 5 of the 
	    Cytoscape Data Services / CPath project.  Our overall goal is to create 
	    the first links in a complete end-to-end CPath database system.  A complete
	    test of this system is defined as follows:  a Cytoscape user loads up the 
	    Cancer "subway" map, exports this data to CPath, opens a web browser,
	    connects to the CPath database, and views the newly submitted data.  If this
	    works, the Phase will be considered complete.
    </P> 
   </section>
   <section name="Development Tasks">
   	<p>
   	   The following represents a list of development tasks (items are
   	   listed in approximate order of development): 
	<UL>
		<LI>Build the CPath Import Table, and Java class(es) for reading/writing
			to this table.  The Import table will contain newly
			imported data for eventual inclusion in the main CPath database.</LI>
		<LI>Build CPath server functionality for submitting PSI data
			from a web form to the database.  This is a file upload feature 
			for submitting data via HTTP Post.</LI>
		<LI>Build the CPath LinkOut Table and Java class(es) for reading/writing
		        to this table.  The LinkOut table will contain references to
			external data bases.</LI>
		<LI>Build a batch tool for transferring data from the CPath Import Table
			to the current GRID tables.</LI>
		<LI>Build batch tool for transferring data from the current GRID 
			tables to the CPath Link Out table.</LI>
		<LI>Modify the current web CPath front-end to use the CPath Link Out
			tables.</LI>
		<LI>Create a data export plugin for exporting data in PSI-MI
			format, and submitting this data to CPath.</LI>
		<LI>Test the system end-to-end with the Cancer "Subway" data.  This
			will take the Subway data in Cytoscape, and export it to CPath.
			We then verify that this data shows up in the CPath web site.</LI>
		<LI>Create a SIF Service for reading SIF files via the local file
			system, HTTP or FTP.  Add this to public data services plugin.</LI>
		<LI>Deploy all new CPath Functionality to CBio.</LI>
		<LI>Release newly updated data services plugin to cytoscape.org.</LI>
	</UL>
    </p>
  </section>
  <section name="Overview of CPath System">
	  <P/>
  	<img src="images/cpath.jpg"/>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
