<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>cPath:  Pathway Database Software</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="About cPath">
        <p>
        cPath is an open source pathway database and software suite designed for
        systems biology research.
        </p>
        <p>
        Main features include:
        <UL>
        <LI>Import pipeline capable of aggregrating pathway and interaction data sets from multiple sources, including:  MINT, IntAct,  HPRD, DIP, BioCyc, KEGG, PUMA2 and Reactome.</LI>
        <LI>Import/Export support for the <A HREF="http://psidev.sourceforge.net/mi/xml/doc/user/">Proteomics Standards Initiative Molecular Interaction</A> (PSI-MI) and the <A HREF="http://www.biopax.org">Biological Pathways Exchange</A> (BioPAX) XML formats.</LI>
        <LI>Data visualization and analysis via <A HREF="http://www.cytoscape.org">Cytoscape</A>.</LI>
        <LI>Simple HTTP URL based XML web service.</LI>
        <LI>Complete software is freely available for local install.  Easy to install and administer.</LI>
        <LI>Partly funded by the U.S. National Cancer Institute, via the <A HREF="https://cabig.nci.nih.gov/">Cancer Biomedical Informatics Grid (caBIG)</A>, and aims to meet "silver-level" requirements for software interoperability and data exchange.</LI>
        </UL>
        </p>
        <p>cPath is currently being developed by the
        <A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org">Computational Biology Center</A>
        at <A HREF="http://www.mskcc.org">Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</A>.
        </p>
        <p>For additional details regarding cPath, please refer to our recent paper:</p>
        <p>
        <UL>
        <LI>Ethan G Cerami, Gary D Bader, Benjamin E Gross, and Chris Sander,
        <b>cPath: open source software for collecting, storing, and querying biological
        pathways</b> BMC Bioinformatics 2006, 7:497 [doi:10.1186/1471-2105-7-497]
        <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=pubmed&amp;cmd=Retrieve&amp;dopt=AbstractPlus&amp;list_uids=17101041&amp;query_hl=2&amp;itool=pubmed_docsum">[Pub Med]</a> <a href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2105/7/497/abstract.">[Full Text]</a>
        </LI>
        </UL>
        </p>
    </section>

    <section name="About the cPath Demo Site">
    <p>
    A demo version of cPath is currently available at:
    <a href="http://cbio.mskcc.org/cpath">http://cbio.mskcc.org/cpath</a>.
    This site is currently running in PSI-MI mode, and contains PSI-MI Level 1 data
    from:
    <A href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/site/index.jsf">IntAct</A> and
    <A href="http://mint.bio.uniroma2.it/mint/Welcome.do">MINT</A>.
    </p>
    </section>

    <section name="cPath Developer Mailing List">
    <p>
    Get involved.  Join the
    <A HREF="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/cpath-dev/">cpath-dev</A> mailing list.
    </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
