<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>cPath Developer Site</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="About cPath">
        <p>
        cPath is an open source pathway database and software suite designed for
        systems biology research.
        </p>
        <p>
        Main features include:
        <UL>
        <LI>Import pipeline capable of aggregrating pathway and interaction data sets from multiple sources, including:  MINT, IntAct,  HPRD, DIP, BioCyc, KEGG, PUMA2 and Reactome.</LI>
        <LI>Import/Export support for the <A HREF="http://psidev.sourceforge.net/mi/xml/doc/user/">Proteomics Standards Initiative Molecular Interaction</A> (PSI-MI) and the <A HREF="http://www.biopax.org">Biological Pathways Exchange</A> (BioPAX) XML formats.</LI>
        <LI>Data visualization and analysis via <A HREF="http://www.cytoscape.org">Cytoscape</A>.</LI>
        <LI>Simple HTTP URL based XML web service.</LI>
        <LI>Complete software is freely available for local install.  Easy to install and administer.</LI>
        <LI>Partly funded by the U.S. National Cancer Institute, via the <A HREF="https://cabig.nci.nih.gov/">Cancer Biomedical Informatics Grid (caBIG)</A>, and aims to meet "silver-level" requirements for software interoperability and data exchange.</LI>
        </UL>
        </p>
        <p>cPath is currently being developed by the
        <A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org">Computational Biology Center</A>
        at <A HREF="http://www.mskcc.org">Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</A>.
        </p>
    </section>
    <section name="About the Developer Site">
    <p>
    The goal of this site is to provide timely information for cPath developers.
    The site is automatically updated every 24 hours, and provides a snapshot
    of all publicly available development work, currently checked into CVS.  Here, you can browse
    the latest JavaDocs, source code, and automatically generated reports.
    You can also browse the latest release notes, installation instructions,
    and technical architecture documents.
    </p>
    </section>

    <section name="cPath Developer Mailing List">
    <p>
    Get involved.  Join the
    <A HREF="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/cpath-dev/">cpath-dev</A> mailing list.
    </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
