<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Release Notes</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

<section name="Release 0.3 Beta">
<P>
<UL>
    <LI>Completely refactored the index/search framework.  Custom field
    search is now available, all search results now support pagination,
    and users can easily search by or browse by organism.  cPath also
    now supports two types of search results:  "interaction view",
    and "protein view."
    </LI>
    <LI>Search Box now supports multiple filters, including an organism
    filter and a custom field filter.</LI>
    <LI>Search Results now appear in a new Search Results Tab.</LI>
    <LI>Added New Tab for Browse by Organism.  Users can sort the organism
    list by name or by number of interactions.</LI>
    <LI>Added New Database Stats Page.  Users can now view number of
    interactors / interactions, plus a list of all imported data sources.</LI>
    <LI>First draft of the cPath FAQ is now complete.</LI>
    <LI>Updated the Web Service API to include revised command names, plus
    a new maxHits parameter.</LI>
    <LI>Changes to the cPath Web Administrator:
        <UL>
            <LI>Administrator can now view/purge the XML Cache.</LI>
            <LI>Administrator can now view/purge the Error Log.</LI>
            <LI>Administrator page now only updates when tasks are active.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Changes to the cPath Command Line Tool:
        <UL>
            <LI>All Administrator Tasks are centralized in a single command line tool.</LI>
            <LI>Administrators can:  import new files, run the full text
            indexer, and run precomputed config files.</LI>
            <LI>Command Line tool supports command line arguments for
            specifying the database user name / password.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>XML Cache is now finalized, and automatically purges itself when
        it hits a maximum number of records.
    </LI>
</UL>
</P>
</section>

<section name="Release 0.2 Beta">
<P>
<UL>
<LI>
Added cPath Administrator Functionality:  Administrator can now run the
full text indexer, and upload files for import.  Administrator can also
monitor long-term tasks, such as importing of large PSI-MI XML documents.
Admin page is now also password-protected.
</LI>
<LI>Created cPath Diagnostics page to perform routine tests and verify
correct installation.
</LI>
<LI>Added support for loading of external references.  Users can use the admin.pl
command line utility or the Admin page to import references.
</LI>
<LI>Added generic framework for pre-computing specific cPath queries.  Queries
can be run from the admin.pl script or set to run on a *nix cron job.
</LI>
<LI>Performed load-testing via Apache JMeter.  JMeter config scripts are now
              available in config/cpath_load_testing_plan.jmx.
</LI>
<LI>Added new page for displaying Interactor specific information, including:
name, organism, and all external references.
</LI>
<LI>Updated the Installation notes to include information re:  cPath
diagnostics page, Tiny Monitor, and "where to look when things go wrong."
</LI>
<LI>Added common stylesheets from <A HREF="http://style.tigris.org">
http://style.tigris.org</A>.
</LI>
<LI>Added HTML filtering for all incoming data to prevent Cross-Site
Scripting attacks.  Implemented recommendations in
<A HREF="http://www.cert.org/tech_tips/malicious_code_mitigation.html">
CERT advisory.</A>
</LI>
</UL>
</P>
</section>
  </body>
</document>