<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Release Notes</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

<section name="Release 0.6 Beta (March, 2006)">
<P>
<UL>
    <LI>Third iteration of support for BioPAX data.
        <UL>
            <LI>Completely redesigned web interface for displaying BioPAX data.</LI>
            <LI>Completely redesigned web interface for searching BioPAX data.</LI>
            <LI>Updated stylesheets.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Newly Expanded Caching Framework
        <UL>
            <LI>All HTML pages are now cached in an in-memory / disk cache, resulting
            in much faster user expeience.</LI>
            <LI>Cache is now persistent across server restarts.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Modifications to the Web Service API:
        <UL>
            <LI>Web service API is now available in two flavors:  PSI-MI mode and
                BioPAX Mode.
            </LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Modifications to the Web based administrator:
        <UL>
            <LI>New section for globally modifying user interface components, such as
            page header, footer, and home page.
            </LI>
            <LI>New section for displaying cache statistics.
            </LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Modifications to the command line administrator tool:
        <UL>
            <LI>All scripts can now operate on multiple database instances, enabling an
                administrator to, for example, maintain two separate instances of cPath
                on the same machine.
            </LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Modifications to the cPath documentation:
        <UL>
            <LI>Completely revised Administrator guide with full details on using the
                revised command line administrator tool.
            </LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>
        Numerous Bug Fixes:
        <UL>
            <LI><A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000682">Bug 682</A></LI>
            <LI><A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000681">Bug 681</A></LI>
            <LI><A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000607">Bug 607</A></LI>
            <LI><A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000551">Bug 551</A></LI>
            <LI><A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000557">Bug 557</A></LI>
            <LI><A HREF="http://cbio.mskcc.org/cytoscape/bugs/bug_view_page.php?bug_id=0000540">Bug 540</A></LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
</UL>
</P>
</section>

<section name="Release 0.5 Beta (December, 2005)">
<P>
<UL>
    <LI>Second iteration of support for BioPAX data.
        <UL>
            <LI>Before saving a new BioPAX pathway, interaction, or
            physical entity, cPath now makes sure that the entity is not
            already stored.  Identity is currently determined via
            Unification XRefs.
            </LI>
            <LI>Upon import of new BioPAX entities, cPath now queries the
            Background Reference subsystem, so that other identifiers, such
            as Affymetrix IDs are added automatically appended.
            </LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Modifications to the Web Services API:
        <UL>
            <LI>New command:  get_top_level_pathway_list.  Retrieves a
            complete list of top-level pathways store in cPath.  A top-level
            pathway is defined as a pathway that contains other
            pathways.  For example, the Reactome Apoptosis pathway
            contains several other pathways, such
            as:  Extrinsic Pathway for Apoptosis, Intrinsic Pathway for
            Apoptosis, etc.  The response to this command is a BioPAX
            XML document.
            </LI>
            <LI>New command:  get_record_by_cpath_id.  Retrieves a BioPAX
            document from cPath.  The response to this command is a BioPAX
            XML document.
            </LI>
            <LI>Note that neither of these commands is documented
            on the Web Service API Help Page.  We did this because we
            needed these new commands ASAP, but did not want to spend
            the time to revisit the web service API in its entirety.
            In a later phase, we place to revisit the API, and these
            commands may change.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
</UL>
</P>
</section>

<section name="Release 0.4 Beta">
<P>
<UL>
    <LI>First iteration of support for BioPAX data.
        <UL>
            <LI>cPath is now capable of importing BioPAX Level 1,2 data.</LI>
            <LI>cPath is now capable of indexing BioPAX Level 1, 2 data.</LI>
            <LI>Web Service API now includes a new "biopax" format.</LI>
            <LI>Bare Bones web view of BioPAX/PSI-MI data is now available.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>cPath now includes a background reference service, providing
        services for protein unification and protein link outs.
    </LI>
</UL>
</P>
</section>

<section name="Release 0.3 Beta">
<P>
<UL>
    <LI>Completely refactored the index/search framework.  Custom field
    search is now available, all search results now support pagination,
    and users can easily search by or browse by organism.  cPath also
    now supports two types of search results:  "interaction view",
    and "protein view."
    </LI>
    <LI>Search Box now supports multiple filters, including an organism
    filter and a custom field filter.</LI>
    <LI>Search Results now appear in a new Search Results Tab.</LI>
    <LI>Added New Tab for Browse by Organism.  Users can sort the organism
    list by name or by number of interactions.</LI>
    <LI>Added New Database Stats Page.  Users can now view number of
    interactors / interactions, plus a list of all imported data sources.</LI>
    <LI>First draft of the cPath FAQ is now complete.</LI>
    <LI>Updated the Web Service API to include revised command names, plus
    a new maxHits parameter.</LI>
    <LI>Changes to the cPath Web Administrator:
        <UL>
            <LI>Administrator can now view/purge the XML Cache.</LI>
            <LI>Administrator can now view/purge the Error Log.</LI>
            <LI>Administrator page now only updates when tasks are active.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>Changes to the cPath Command Line Tool:
        <UL>
            <LI>All Administrator Tasks are centralized in a single command line tool.</LI>
            <LI>Administrators can:  import new files, run the full text
            indexer, and run precomputed config files.</LI>
            <LI>Command Line tool supports command line arguments for
            specifying the database user name / password.</LI>
        </UL>
    </LI>
    <LI>XML Cache is now finalized, and automatically purges itself when
        it hits a maximum number of records.
    </LI>
</UL>
</P>
</section>

<section name="Release 0.2 Beta">
<P>
<UL>
<LI>
Added cPath Administrator Functionality:  Administrator can now run the
full text indexer, and upload files for import.  Administrator can also
monitor long-term tasks, such as importing of large PSI-MI XML documents.
Admin page is now also password-protected.
</LI>
<LI>Created cPath Diagnostics page to perform routine tests and verify
correct installation.
</LI>
<LI>Added support for loading of external references.  Users can use the admin.pl
command line utility or the Admin page to import references.
</LI>
<LI>Added generic framework for pre-computing specific cPath queries.  Queries
can be run from the admin.pl script or set to run on a *nix cron job.
</LI>
<LI>Performed load-testing via Apache JMeter.  JMeter config scripts are now
              available in config/cpath_load_testing_plan.jmx.
</LI>
<LI>Added new page for displaying Interactor specific information, including:
name, organism, and all external references.
</LI>
<LI>Updated the Installation notes to include information re:  cPath
diagnostics page, Tiny Monitor, and "where to look when things go wrong."
</LI>
<LI>Added common stylesheets from <A HREF="http://style.tigris.org">
http://style.tigris.org</A>.
</LI>
<LI>Added HTML filtering for all incoming data to prevent Cross-Site
Scripting attacks.  Implemented recommendations in
<A HREF="http://www.cert.org/tech_tips/malicious_code_mitigation.html">
CERT advisory.</A>
</LI>
</UL>
</P>
</section>
  </body>
</document>