<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>To Do List</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="To Do List">
        <p>
<source>
This document contains cPath Items we want to implement someday:

cPath Functionality Issues:
----------------------------
0.  We still don't have any way of adding new external databases,
    and the controlled vocabulary terms and URLs associated with each database.
    As a first step, we should definitely add a command line script to
    do this.
    --->  current priority:  I think this is relatively high.

1.  Add Field Specific Lucene Searching, e.g. "name:RAS".
    ---> current priority:  low.
    [NOW COMPLETE]

2.  Add new query:  query by experimental method (e.g. all the data from
    two-hybrid)
	---> current priority:  hi.
    [NOW COMPLETE]

3.  Add Indexing of interactions.
    Requires changes to web interface.  Needs more exploration.
    ---> current priority:  low.
    [NOW COMPLETE]

4.  For HTML front end of cPath query API: pageinate results
    (only text index results currently paginated)
	---> current priority:  low.
    [NOW COMPLETE]

5.  Import Complete Data Set

    From Gary:  DIP, MINT and IntAct now all have downloadable full data
    sets.  We should think about creating an official inhouse release of cpath
    containing all of the data we can get (since the DIP data is proprietary, we
    can't give it to anyone else externally).
    [Will be implemented in Phase 9]

4.  Modify Cytoscape PlugIn to recognize n-ary interactions when n > 2.
	-->  current priority:  high

5.  Use IntAct External Database File

    From Gary:  "I just noticed that the IntAct database is maintaining a small
    file of external databases
    http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/intact/intactCore/data/
    controlledVocab/CvDatabase.def?rev=1.7&amp;view=auto

    We might be able to eventually collaborate with them on this list.
    Something to just keep in mind."

6.  Build a Front-end administrative interface to the External Database Tables
	(more details are included in phase 6 doc, before being deferred)
	---> current priority:  low.

7.  Provide query API functionality to get a list of valid query API commands.
	E.g. for getInteractionsBySource, we could have getValidSources
	---> current priority:  low.

8.  Add getExternalReferences to query API.  This would allow e.g. Cytoscape
	to easily create external links.
	---> current priority:  medium.

9.  Support content-length calculation of PSI-MI queries, where possible,
    to support more accurate progress metering on the client side.  We might
    be able to easily do it for queries that are cached and for the precomputed
    queries.  For queries that aren't, we could at least provide
    updates of the parsing progress as it happens (Rob's idea)
	---> Current priority: low.

11.  Resolve cross-species interaction issue.

12. Implement a full database/ web  statistics page.
    This could be precomputed regularly (e.g. weekly), not computed on the
    fly.  The best example of a stats page is currently the MINT page:
    http://160.80.34.4/mint/statistics/statistics.php
	---> Current priority: low.

13. Add support to cPath and data services layer for importing PSI-MI files
    that contain interactions with more than two proteins (e.g. 5 protein complex).  This would allow us to
    import data from the PIN database in the Tempst lab at MSKCC
    (http://pin.mskcc.org).
	---> Current priority: medium.

15.  Create an advanced query system for xml records that supports xquery or
     something similar. This could regularly index XML from cpath for advanced
     queries.  Only internal users would use this system and it would probably
     be slow.  Investigate databases that support xpath or libraries such as OJB.

16.  Add generic support for an ontology data objects.

    From Gary:  "As per our discussion today regarding PSI-MI controlled
    vocabularies, here is an implementation of a basic hierarchy from the
    GK project.

    Example 1:
    http://www.genomeknowledge.org/cgi-bin/classbrowser?DB=gk_current

    Example 2:
    http://www.genomeknowledge.org/cgi-bin/eventbrowser?DB=gk_current&amp;
    ID=69231&amp;PREVIOUS_ID=69236&amp;RORDER=69278&amp;E=69236&amp;E=69278

    (mind the wrapping)

    I'm not saying that we should implement this scheme eventually, we should
    just note the example.

cPath Performance/Reliability/Security Issues
---------------------------------------------
1.  Set up auto-emails upon fatal cPath errors (how does a user deal with errors?).

Data Service Specific Items:
-----------------------------
1.  Add Gene Name/Synonym Look up to data services (requires a back-end, may
    be able to use Entrez Gene DB).

2.  Create a service for reading in Cytoscape node/edge attributes to go with
    sif reader.

3.  Create an "About Data Services PlugIn", with version #, list of all
    registered (more details are included in phase 6 doc, before being deferred)
	---> current priority:  low.

4.  Resurrect the GRID Plugin - retrieves data from GRID directly into Cytoscape
</source>
        </p>
     </section>
  </body>
</document>
